Finding aid to the William Sentam Taylor papers. CA.MS.01154
Smith College Archives
William Sentam Taylor papers
1920-1993
Smith College Archives
Taylor, William Sentam
CA.MS.01154
1.771 linear feet (5 containers)
William Sentam Taylor was a professor of psychology at Smith College. The collection contains the publications, correspondence, manuscripts, memorabilia, and news clippings of William and his wife, Phoebe (Smith) Taylor.
Conditions Governing Access
Until we move into New Neilson in early 2021, collections are stored in multiple locations and may take up to 48 hours to retrieve. Researchers are strongly encouraged to contact Special Collections (specialcollections@smith.edu) at least a week in advance of any planned visits so that boxes may be retrieved for them in a timely manner.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Biographical / Historical
William Sentam Taylor spent his childhood in a Presbyterian Manse. He earned his B.A. in 1916 at Gettysburg College in psychology and then in 1921, after taking some time off school to teach at Gettysburg and to work in the US Navy Reserve Medical Corps at the Naval Prison of Deer Island, he earned his Ph.D. in philosophy from Harvard University. Before coming to Smith College as professor of psychology in 1926, Taylor taught at Bryn Mawr (1921-1922), the University of Wisconsin (1922-1923) and the University of Maine (1923-1926). While teaching at Smith, Taylor was a member of Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi, the American Psychopathological Association, the American Board of Examiners in Psychological Hypnosis and the Massachusetts Board of Certification in Psychology. He wrote a number of articles on abnormal psychology, mental hygiene, and hypnosis, but his greatest works were Dynamic and Abnormal Psychology (1954) and The Human Course: Collected Thoughts for Living (1974), which he published with his wife. Taylor also taught as a visiting professor at Harvard University, the University of Chicago, and the University of Massachusetts, before retiring from Smith in 1962. He died in 1976.
Phoebe (Smith) Taylor, wife of William S. Taylor, was born in Eau Claire Wisconsin in 1895 to Edward and Sarah (Gallett) Smith. She received her bachelor's degree from the University of Wisconsin in English. Mrs. Taylor's work covered a wide range of creative endeavors, from sculpting bas-relief portraits of professors in the 1930's and 40's to the huge volume of articles she wrote during her life, largely on education and New England History. She was a member of the Round Hill Club and was president of the Smith College Faculty Wives. She had two daughters with William Taylor, Cicely Taylor Buckley, and Phoebe Taylor Lansdale, as well as five grandchildren at the time of her death. She died in Northampton Nursing Home in 1993.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the professional and personal files of William Sentam Taylor and Phoebe (Smith) Taylor. These include William Taylor's professional correspondence, publications, speeches and manuscripts. The collection also includes documents on his activities outside Smith as a member of various groups concerned with political freedom and democracy, including correspondence, letters to various newspapers, membership cards, and brochures and pamphlets published by the various organizations. The collection also contains the papers of Phoebe Taylor, including articles about her career and life, her published works, and professional and personal correspondence.
Psychology--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts --Northampton.; Taylor, William Sentam; Taylor, William Sentam; Taylor, Phoebe, 1895-1993
- Index, no date (Box 1031.1, Folder 1)
- Biography – General, 1929-1976 (Box 1031.1, Folder 2)
- Biography – Honors, 1962-1967 (Box 1031.1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence – General, 1959-1973 (Box 1031.1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence – AAUP at Smith, 1927-1964 (Box 1031.1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence – Course Material, 1961-1968 (Box 1031.1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence – Curriculum, 1945-1950 (Box 1031.1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence – Organization of Smith College, 1961-1968 (Box 1031.1, Folder 8)
- Lecture given to the SSCH, 1961 (Box 1031.1, Folder 9)
- Manuscripts – Index, no date (Box 1032, Folder 1)
- Manuscripts – "A Theory of Learning", 1963-1976 (Box 1032, Folder 2)
- Manuscripts – "Up from Anarchy", no date (Box 1032, Folder 3)
- Manuscripts – "Will, Freedom, and Responsibility", 1962-1966 (Box 1032, Folder 4)
- Manuscripts – Miscellaneous, 1956-1958 (Box 1032, Folder 5)
- Manuscripts – Correspondence – Unpublished Chapters Dynamic and Abnormal Psychology, 1955-1975 (Box 1032, Folder 6)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – Art as Adjustment, no date (Box 1032, Folder 7)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – Dreams, no date (Box 1032, Folder 8)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – From Magic to Abnormal Psychology, no date (Box 1032, Folder 9)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – Historical Approach to Abnormal Psychology, no date (Box 1032, Folder 10)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – Hypnosis, no date (Box 1032, Folder 11)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – Meaning and Symbols, no date (Box 1032, Folder 12)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – Psychotherapy, no date (Box 1032, Folder 13)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – The Self, no date (Box 1032, Folder 14)
- Manuscripts – Unpublished Chapters – Synesthesia, no date (Box 1032, Folder 15)
- Index for Collected Materials on Democracy, no date (Box 1033, Folder 1)
- Air Raid Precautions, World War II, 1941-1942 (Box 1033, Folder 2)
- American Civil Liberties Union, 1939-1969 (Box 1033, Folder 3)
- American Committee for Cultural Freedom, 1942-1956 (Box 1033, Folder 4)
- Americans for Democratic Action, 1947-1956 (Box 1033, Folder 5)
- Censorship and Freedom, 1935-1938 (Box 1033, Folder 6)
- City Manager Plan, 1933-1938 (Box 1033, Folder 7)
- Civil Liberties; Freedom of Speech, 1935-1939 (Box 1033, Folder 8)
- Communists and Fascists, 1942 (Box 1033, Folder 9)
- Cooperatives, 1935-1977 (Box 1033, Folder 10)
- Daughters of the American Revolution, 1928 (Box 1033, Folder 11)
- Democratic Nomination, 1949 (Box 1033, Folder 12)
- Democracy, 1946-1974 (Box 1033, Folder 13)
- "Essence of Democracy" and "What is Democracy?" by WST, 1945 (Box 1033, Folder 14)
- Faculty Balloting Reports, 1958 (Box 1033, Folder 15)
- Federal Council of the Church of Christ, 1944 (Box 1033, Folder 16)
- Fluoridation, 1953 (Box 1033, Folder 17)
- Half-Mast, 1958 (Box 1033, Folder 18)
- Intellectual Freedom, 1940-1962 (Box 1033, Folder 19)
- Interdependence, International Society on Standards, Humanist Unity, 1952-1953 (Box 1033, Folder 20)
- Liberal Citizens of Massachusetts, 1952-1959 (Box 1033, Folder 21)
- Massachusetts Citizens Committee, 1943 (Box 1033, Folder 22)
- New America, 1940-1941 (Box 1033, Folder 23)
- "On Birth Control" by WST, 1948 (Box 1033, Folder 24)
- Pro-chairmanship, 1961 (Box 1033, Folder 25)
- "The Professor's Dilemma: The Economic Status of the Profession" by WST, 1945 (Box 1033, Folder 26)
- "Three Methods of Voting" by WST, 1947-1958 (Box 1033, Folder 27)
- Vivisection, 1956 (Box 1033, Folder 28)
- List of Publications, no date (Box 1034, Folder 1)
- Publications – Editorials, 1936-1948 (Box 1034, Folder 2)
- Publications – "Dynamic and Abnormal Psychology", 1955 (Box 1034, Folder 3)
- Publications – "The Human Course", 1974-1975 (Box 1034, Folder 4)
- Publications – "Multiple Personality", 1944 (Box 1034, Folder 5)
- Publications – "The Problem of 'The God Locomotive'", 1929 (Box 1034, Folder 6)
- Publications – "Rationalization and its Social Significance", 1923 (Box 1034, Folder 7)
- Publications – "Readings in Abnormal Psychology and Mental Hygiene", 1927-1928 (Box 1034, Folder 8)
- Publications – "Science in Modern Education", 1962 (Box 1034, Folder 9)
- Publications – "The Subconscious", 1960 (Box 1034, Folder 10)
- Publications – "Therapy of Multiple Personality", 1970-1971 (Box 1034, Folder 11)
- Publications – "The Virtues of Learning Curves", 1935 (Box 1034, Folder 12)
- Publications – "Why Not Censureship?", 1935 (Box 1034, Folder 13)
- Publications – Reviews, 1929-1973 (Box 1034, Folder 14)
- Publications – Miscellaneous, 1920-1961 (Box 1034, Folder 15)
- Publications – Belief and Behavior, 1921 (Box 1034, Folder 16)
- Family – Taylor, Phoebe (Mrs. William Taylor), 1936-1993 (Box 1035, Folder 1)
- Family – Taylor, Phoebe – correspondence, 1962-1992 (Box 1035, Folder 2)
- Family – Taylor, Phoebe "The Free Life", 1987-1988 (Box 1035, Folder 3)